Guide to the Walt Whitman Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Walt Whitman collection
1842-1949
YCAL MSS 202
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.65
(18 boxes) + 1 broadside folder, 7 art storage objects
The Whitman collection consists of letters, manuscripts, photographs, artwork, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Walt Whitman. There is personal and business correspondence from Whitman to family, friends, editors, and publishers, including Richard Maurice Bucke, John Burroughs, Julius Chambers, Moncure Conway, Nathan Hale, James R. Osgood and Company, George Routledge & Sons, William Sloane Kennedy, William Michael Rossetti, John Swinton, and Louisa Whitman. There are letters to Whitman from Civil War soldiers and from a number of writers, including Samuel Clemens, John Camden Hotten, William Douglas O'Connor, Allen Thorndike Rice, and Algernon Swinburne. There is also a small group of third-party correspondence to Whitman scholar George Rice Carpenter. Whitman's writings are well represented in the Rabinowitz and Van Sinderen gifts. The Writings subseries in the Van Sinderen gift includes subdivisions for autobiographical writings, diaries, lectures and speeches, notes and notebooks, outlines and proposals, poetry and the writing of others. The writings are present chiefly in galley proofs, many corrected and signed, and holograph manuscripts. Photographs and artistic representations of Whitman include work by well-known nineteenth century photographers, studios, and artists. There are photographs by Thomas Eakins, William Kurtz, Major & Knapp Engraving, and Brady National Photographic Art Gallery. Works of art include a bust of Whitman by Samuel Murray, a woodcut by Bertrand Zadig, and engravings by Samuel Hollyer, William James Linton, and Stephen Alonzo Schoff. Also of note are papers relating to George Whitman and New York Civil War regiments.
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Walt Whitman Collection was acquired through various gifts and purchases dating from 1911.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 16-18: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or related to Walt Whitman, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. The collection contains letters, manuscripts, photographs, and personal papers, and spans the years 1842-1949.
The collection is housed in 17 boxes and organized by provenance into six series: Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, Walter Gierasch Gift, Mrs. Bernard Gimbel Gift, Louis Mayer Rabinowitz Gift, Adrian Van Sinderen Gift, and Material from Other Sources. Boxes 12-15 contain Oversize material. Boxes 16-17 contain Restricted Fragile material.
Series I, Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, is organized into two subseries: Letters from Walt Whitman and Writings of Walt Whitman.
The correspondence includes brief letters to Anne Botta, Whitman biographer Richard Maurice Bucke, and naturalist John Burroughs. There are two letters to Thomas Nicholson, one describing Whitman's experience in Canada in the summer of 1880, and six letters to James R. Osgood and Company dating from mid-late 1881, concerning an edition of Leaves of Grass. Letters deal with copyright, presswork, and other issues related to the production of the book. The Writings of Walt Whitman includes a holograph manuscript of "Two Rivulets" and a corrected galley for the poem "Thou Who Hast Slept..."
Series II, Walter Gierasch Gifts, is also organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Writings.
The correspondence consists of one typescript extract of a letter from Whitman to William Sloane Kennedy and several third-party letters, dating from 1902-1908, to Whitman scholar and biographer George R. Carpenter. There are letters from Charles Bastide, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Curtis Hidden Page, Fred Scott Newton, and others. The Writings subseries includes an extract of Whitman's Notes and Fragments.
Series III, Mrs. Bernard Gimbel Gift, is organized into three small subseries: Letters from Walt Whitman, Photographs, and Other Papers.
There are four letters from Whitman, one each to E. S. Marsh and John Swinton, and two to unidentified individuals. There are three photographs of Whitman, several printed reproductions of photographs, and a colored version of the Samuel Hollyer engraving that served as the frontispiece in the first edition (1855) of Leaves of Grass.
Series IV, Louis Mayer Rabinowitz Gift, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings of Walt Whitman, and Other Papers.
The correspondence is subdivided for Letters to Whitman and Other Correspondence. Letters to Whitman consists of 14 letters from Civil War soldiers and former patients dating from 1865-1870. Most letters are brief, "a few lines," written to inform Whitman of the correspondent's health and whereabouts. Some mention Whitman's work and mutual friends, express interest in meeting, and seek favors, including help in obtaining work. Other Correspondence consists of third-party correspondence, with one letter, from H. F. to Elmira Crossman, in Whitman's hand.
The Writings subseries includes several galley proofs for individual articles and poems, some inscribed and signed by Whitman, as well as an untitled holograph manuscript on writing, a holograph note titled "Incidents for Soldiers in the Ranks," and holograph fragments of November Boughs.
Other Papers contains two groups of papers, one concerning Whitman's brother George and one concerning New York Civil War regiments. The papers relating to George Whitman, dating from 1864-65, include journal entries and letters documenting Whitman's efforts to determine the health and location of his brother during the war. Whitman's journal entries provide a rough history of his brother's movements. There is an undated memo from George Whitman, enclosed with a "Feb. 19th, 1865" letter from Captain William Cook to Louisa Whitman, in which he reveals his captivity in Virginia and reassures his family that he is "in tip top health and spirits." Whitman's first journal entry, dated December 26, 1864, describes the family's experience after receiving George's army trunk, which appears to have been shipped home after George went missing or was taken prisoner. Whitman writes, "It stood some hours before we felt inclined to open it." The papers concerning New York Civil War regiments include newspaper clippings, holograph notes, and two notebooks on the 51st New York Veterans.
Series V, Adrian Van Sinderen Gift, housed in boxes 2-9, is organized into five series: Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, Artwork and Objects, and Other Papers.
Correspondence, housed in box 2, is organized into subdivisions for Letters from Walt Whitman, Letters to Walt Whitman, and Third-party Letters. There is correspondence from Whitman to John Burroughs, Julius Chambers, Moncure Conway, Boston editor Nathan Hale, William Sloane Kennedy, William Michael Rossetti, John Swinton, his mother Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, and others. There are brief letters to editors and individuals regarding manuscripts and books, including a translation of Leaves of Grass into Russian. The two largest groups of letters, to John Burroughs and Louisa Van Velsor Whitman, are personal in nature. There are incoming letters from family members, Richard Maurice Bucke, and a number of journalists and writers, including Samuel Clemens, John Camden Hotten, William Douglas O'Connor, Allen Thorndike Rice, and Algernon Swinburne. Third-party Correspondence includes letters from Edward Dowden, H. Buxton Forman, Edmund Clarence Stedman, Horace Traubel, and John Townsend Trowbridge.
The Writings subseries, housed in box 3, consists chiefly of work by Whitman. There are articles and essays, autobiographical writings, a diary fragment, lectures and speeches, notes and notebooks, outlines and proposals, and poetry. Writings are present in manuscript, corrected galley proofs, and printed versions. In addition, there are proofs of two Robert Green Ingersoll pieces on Whitman.
The Van Sinderen Gift includes small subseries, housed in box 4, for Photographs, Artwork and Objects, and Other Papers. The Photographs subseries consists chiefly of studio portraits of Whitman dating from the 1870-80s; many photographs are signed. There are numerous artistic representations of Whitman, including woodcuts by Gustav Kruell and Bertrand Zadig, engravings by Samuel Hollyer, an oil painting by George W. Waters, and a bust by Samuel Murray. There are also etchings, lithographs, and medallions. The Other Papers subseries includes, among other miscellaneous items, Whitman's last pair of eyeglasses.
There are 57 cases accompanying the Van Sinderen manuscript material. Manuscripts and letters were removed and the cases stored separately in boxes 5-9.
Series VI, Material from Other Sources, housed in boxes 10-11, consists of single and small gifts and purchases from various sources. Provenance is documented when known on individual folders. The series is organized into five subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, Artwork, and Other Papers.
The Correspondence subseries is organized into three subvidisions: Letters from Walt Whitman, Letters to Walt Whitman, and Third-Party Correspondence. There are letters from Whitman to George Routledge, William James Linton, and others. Whitman's letters are of a business nature. His letter to Routledge, for example, confirms an agreement for "$50 in gold" for use of an unnamed poem. Other correspondents include Karl Knortz.
Writings includes work by Whitman and others. There are holograph manuscripts for a poem, "Sea-Captains, Young or Old," and an untitled autobiographical statement. The autobiographical statement, written in 1888, discusses Whitman's service to the wounded in Maryland and Virginia during the Civil War from 1862 to 1865. There are several galley proofs for other Whitman poems and for Louis Untermeyer's The Poetry and Prose of Walt Whitman.
The Photographs and Artwork subseries contain the work of well-known 19th century photographers and artists. There are photographs of Whitman by Thomas Eakins and sculptor Samuel Murray, and both original engravings and reproductions of work by Samuel Hollyer, Gustav Kruell, William James Linton, and Stephen Alonzo Schoff.
Oversize material, housed in boxes 12-15, contains items from Series IV-VI. Restricted Fragile material is housed in boxes 16-17.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Engravings (prints); Photographic prints; Authors; Bucke, Richard Maurice, 1837-1902; Burroughs, John, 1837-1921; Carpenter, George R. (George Rice), 1863-1909; Chambers, Julius, 1850-1920; Conway, Moncure Daniel, 1832-1907; Eakins, Thomas, 1844-1916; Hale, Nathan, 1784-1863; Hollyer, Samuel, 1826-1919; Hotten, John Camden, 1832-1873; Kennedy, William Sloane, 1850-1929; Kurtz, William, 1833-1904; Linton, W. J. (William James), 1812-1897; Murray, S. (Samuel); O'Connor, William Douglas, 1832-1889; Rice, Allen Thorndike, 1851-1889; Rossetti, William Michael, 1829-1919; Schoff, Stephen Alonzo, 1818-1904; Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909; Swinton, John, 1829-1901; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Whitman, George Washington, 1829-1901; Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor, 1795-1873; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Zadig, Bertrand; Whitman family; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 51st (1861-1865); Brady's National Photographic Portrait Galleries; George Routledge and Sons; James R. Osgood and Company; Major & Knapp Engraving, Manufacturing & Lithographic Co
- Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, 1867-1888; Series I; 8
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Owen Franklin Aldis, 1911
  - LETTERS FROM WALT WHITMAN
    - Botta, Anne C. (Anne Charlotte Lynch), 1871 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bucke, R.[ichard?] M.[aurice?], 18[88?] Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Burroughs, John, 1867 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - James R. Osgood and Company, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Nicholson, Thomas, 1880-81 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - WRITINGS OF WALT WHITMAN
    - November Boughs, page proofs, 1888 Oct 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Thou Who Hast Slept All Night Upon the Storm," galley proof, corrected, with proofreaders' marks, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes "When the Full-Grown Poet Came"
    - Two Rivulets, holograph fragments, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Walter Gierasch Gift, 1887-1908; Series II; 8
  Gift of Walter Gierasch, 1951
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Walt Whitman
      - Kennedy, William Sloane, 1887, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Typescript copies
    - Third-Party Correspondence to George Rice Carpenter
      - Bastide, Charles, 1906 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Dart, John Kernan, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1902 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Includes typescript copies of correspondence between Higginson, William Sloane Kennedy, and Ethel Parton
      - Page, Curtis Hidden, 1908 Sep 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Scott, Fred Newton, 1907 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Includes enclosure
  - WRITINGS
    - Whitman, Walt
      - Notes and Fragments, extracts, typescript (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Morgan, Charlotte Elizabeth
      - "The Early Writings of Walt Whitman," thesis, typescript, corrected, 1905 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Mrs. Bernard Gimbel Gift, 1855-1887; Series III; 7
  Gift of Mrs. Bernard Gimbel, 1958
  - LETTERS FROM WALT WHITMAN
    - Marsh, [E. S.], 1883 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Swinton, John, [1878] Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified, 1885 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Major & Knapp Engraving, Manufacturing & Lithographic Co., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Sarony & Co.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Major & Knapp Engraving, Manufacturing & Lithographic Co., Box 1, folder 20
    - Unidentified, 1887, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Samuel Hollyer engraving, [1855?] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Printed ephemera, 1887, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Louis Mayer Rabinowitz Gift, 1863-1891; Series IV; 36
  Gift of Louis Mayer Rabinowitz, 1946
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters to Walt Whitman
      - Bainbridge, Thomas, 1870 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Bainbridge, William F., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Cole, George D., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Emerson, Ralph Waldo
        See: Writings, Other Writings, Box 1, folder 54
      - Flood, John, 1869 [Jan?] 11 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Heywood, Ezra H. (Ezra Hervey)
      - Kelly, Milton, 1867 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Millis, William H., 1868 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Pratt, John B., 1870 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Reed, Milford [C.?], 1868 Ma 26 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Stewart, William, 1865 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Thompson, H. B., 1869 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Williamson, ----, 1868 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Winant, Stephen K., 1870 May (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Wise, Alfred, 1868 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Other Correspondence
      - Corson, A. to unidentified, 1870 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Crossman, H. F. to Elmira Crossman, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 38)
        AL from H. F. to Elmira Crossman in Whitman's hand; includes letter from Eimira to H. F. Crossman
      - Winstanley, Henry to [John O'Connor], [1863?] Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 39)
        Includes note in Whitman's hand
      - "Ell" to unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - WRITINGS OF WALT WHITMAN
    - Articles and essays
      - "The Bible as Poetry," galley proof, [ca. 1883 Feb] (Box Bsd, folder 41)
      - "Fifty-First New-York City Veterans," galley proof (7 copies, 2 annotated), 1864 Oct 29
      - "The Soldiers, &c," galley proof, 1865 Feb
      - ["Understand that you can have in your writing..."], holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Poetry
      - "Ah, Not this Granite Dead and Cold," galley proof, inscribed, 1885 Feb (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - "As the Greek's Signal Flame," galley proof, inscribed, [ca. 1887 Dec] (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - "A Carol Closing Sixty-Nine," galley proof, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - "Going Somewhere," galley proof, inscribed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - "Shak[e]spe[a]re-Bacon's Cipher," galley proof, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - "Thanks in Old Age," galley proof, inscribed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - "To a Common Prostitute," printed version, The Word, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - "To Get the Final Lilt of Songs," galley proof, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - "Twilight," galley proof, inscribed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
      - "Walt Whitman's Last "Good-Bye My Fancy"," holograph manuscript, corrected, [ca. 1891] (Box 1, Folder 52)
        Includes letter to Whitman from A. F. Hilliard, dated May 25, 1891, on verso
    - Other Writings
      - "Incidents, for Soldiers in the Ranks," holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - ["J.R. Osgood & Co.: Dear Sirs..."], open letter, printed version, Leaflet Literature, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
        Includes letters to Whitman from Ezra H. Heywood and R.[alph] W.[aldo] Emerson
      - November Boughs, holograph fragments, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Papers relating to George Whitman, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Papers relating to New York Civil War regiments, 1863-67, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57-59)
- Adrian Van Sinderen Gift, 1842-1925; Series V; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  Gift of Adrian Van Sinderen, 1940
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Walt Whitman
      - Abdy-Williams, E. M., 1885 Jan 7 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - Burroughs, John, [1873?]-88 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - Chambers, [Julius], 1888 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - Conway, Moncure D.[aniel], 1887 Mar 19 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      - The Daily Picayune, 1887 Jan 17 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - [Eldridge, Charles W.?], 1864 (Box 2, Folder 65)
      - Hale, Nathan (1784-1863), 1842 Jun (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - Johnston, John H., 1876-90 (Box 2, Folder 67)
        Includes printed letter from Whitman to W. M. Rossetti dated March 17, 1876
      - [Kennedy, William Sloane?], 1891 Aug 20 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Lee, J. Fitzgerald, 1881 Dec 20 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - Rossetti, William Michael, 1867 Dec 3
        See: Johnston, John H., Box 2, folder 67
      - [Scovel, James Matlock?], 1890 Dec 5 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - Swinton, John, 1878 Jun 11 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - W. H. Piper and Co., 1871 Dec 8 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 73)
        Includes photograph of Walt Whitman
      - Wilde, Oscar, [1882] Jan 18 (Box 2, Folder 74)
        ANS in unidentified hand
      - Unidentified, 1866-87 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - Empty envelopes, 1889, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Letters to Walt Whitman
      - Bucke, Richard Maurice (1837-1902), 1888 Apr 25 (Box 2, Folder 77)
      - Burkhardt, Charles A.
        See: Writings, Articles, Box 3, folder 112
      - Burroughs, John (1837-1921), 1886, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 78)
      - Bush, Alonzo, 1863 Dec 22 (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - Campbell, Charles B.
      - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1889 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      - Eldridge, Charles W., 1883 Sep 22 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      - Hotten, John Camden (1832-1873), 1868 Apr 8 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      - Kennedy, William Sloane (1850-1929), 1884-89, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 83)
      - O'Connor, William Douglas, 1882, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      - Rice, Allen Thorndike, 1881 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 85)
      - Swinburne, A.[lgernon?], C.[harles?], [1868?] Mar 26 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      - Twain, Mark
        See: Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, Box 2, folder 80
      - United States. Attorney General, 1874 Jun 30 (Box 2, Folder 87)
      - Wentworth, Horace, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      - Whitman family, 1875, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      - Whitman, Louisa Van Velsor, [ca. 1870-76] (Box 2, Folder 90)
      - Whitman, Thomas Jefferson, 1873 Mar 16 (Box 2, Folder 91)
        See also: Writings, Articles, Box 3, folder 121
      - Worthington, Richard, 1879, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      - Empty envelopes, 1872-97 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Third-Party Letters
      - Burroughs, John to "Mr. Pomeroy", 1879 Oct 5 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      - Davis, Mary O. to J. H. Johnston
        See: Other Papers, Box 4, folder 199
      - Dowden, Edward to Alexander Strahan, 1871 Apr 11 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Forman, H. Buxton (Harry Buxton) to "J. Davy & Sons", 1885 Jun 19 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - Hartmann, Sadakichi to "Dr. Wiksell", 1920 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - James R. Osgood and Company to [William?] Winter, 1871 Oct 6 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - Johnstone, John to [Edward] Dowden, 1898 Jun 3 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Keller, E.[lizabeth Leavitt?] to "Mr. Powers", 1903 Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - Kennedy, William Sloane to [Laurens?] Maynard, 1897 Jun 10 (Box 2, Folder 101)
      - O'Connor, William Douglas to Abby H. Price, 1866 Jan 11 (Box 2, Folder 102)
      - Rossetti, William Michael to The Sun, [1868?] Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 103)
      - Stead, W. T. (William Thomas) to [Richard?] Le Gallienne, 1894 Oct 20 (Box 2, Folder 104)
      - Stedman, Edmund C.[larence?] to Horatio C. King, 1884 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 105)
      - [Stedman, Edmund Clarence?] to unidentified
        See: Writings, Poetry, "Song of the Univeral"
      - Traubel, [Horace] to [William F.?] Gable, 1908 Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 106)
      - Trowbridge, J. T. (John Townsend) to [William?] Cushing Bainburgh, 1885 Dec 21 (Box 2, Folder 107)
      - Unidentified to "Mr. Goldsmith", [19]22 Feb 24 (Box 2, Folder 108)
      - Empty envelopes, 1921 Dec 21 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - WRITINGS
    - Articles and Essays
      - "Death of Carlyle," galley proof, [ca. 1881]
      - ["It has been good fun to-day..."], holograph manuscript, corrected, [1872?] (Box 3, Folder 110)
      - Lafayette in Brooklyn, typescript fragments, corrected, with notes in unidentified hand (Box 3, Folder 111)
      - "An Old Man's Rejoinder"
        - Holograph manuscript, corrected, 1890 Aug 4 (Box 3, Folder 112)
          Includes envelope and letters to Whitman from A. Edward Newton, Charles A. Burkhardt, Charles B. Campbell, and others on verso of manuscript leaves
        - Galley proof, [ca. 1890 Aug]
      - "Old Poets," galley proof, [ca. 1890 Nov]
      - "Poetry of the Future," holograph fragment, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 113)
      - "Policeman Doyle," holograph manuscript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 114)
      - "Preface"
        - Holograph, corrected, 1890 Sep 24 (Box 3, Folder 115)
        - Galley proof, corrected, 1890 Sep
      - "Real American Red Men," holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 116)
      - "The Soldiers, &c," galley proof, 1865 Feb
      - "A Thought on Shak[e]speare," galley proof, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 117)
      - "Walt Whitman's Poem To-day at Dartmouth College," holograph manuscript, corrected, [1872?] Jun 26 (Box 3, Folder 118)
        Includes poem, ["As a strong bird, on pinions free..."], printed version
      - "Washington as a Central Winter Residence," holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 119)
      - "Wealth of Poets," holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 120)
      - "A Word About Tennyson," holograph manuscript fragments, corrected, [ca. 1888] (Box 3, Folder 121)
        Includes letter to Whitman from Thomas Jefferson Whitman
    - Autobiographical Writings
      - "Convalescent Hours," holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 122)